<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
				<title type="main" xml:lang="bo-Latn-x-wylie">tshad ma rnam par nges pa'i ti ka legs par bshad pa bsdus pa</title>
            <author ref="apis:3839">gtsang nag pa brtson 'grus seng ge</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed by</resp>
               <name ref="corpusmd:PH">Pascale Hugon</name>
               <name ref="corpusmd:YF">Yoichi Fukuda</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI Markup by</resp>
               <name ref="corpusmd:TD">Tsering Drongshar</name>
               <name ref="corpusmd:PH">Pascale Hugon</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Translation(s) by</resp>
               <name ref="corpusmd:KK">Kazuo Kano</name>
               <name ref="corpusmd:PH">Pascale Hugon</name>
               <name ref="corpusmd:KC">Kyeongjin Choi</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data Modelling</resp>
               <name ref="corpusmd:RG">Rachael Griffiths</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>APIS named entitites database implementation</resp>
               <name ref="corpusmd:SB">Saranya Balasubramanian</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>APIS named entitites database implementation</resp>
               <name ref="corpusmd:SR">Stephan Resch</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML editor cumstomization</resp>
               <name ref="corpus.:DStx">Daniel Stoxreiter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>ODD Implementation</resp>
               <name ref="corpusmd:DS">Daniel Schopper</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Supervision</resp>
               <name ref="corpusmd:DS">Daniel Schopper</name>
            </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>Digital Edition in Wylie with TEI Markup</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Academy of Sciences</publisher>
            <availability status="public">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>The Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0) licence applies to this document.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TibSchol">1_013_01</idno>
            <date>2023</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         <physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><dimensions unit="cm" scope="width x height"></dimensions></support></supportDesc></objectDesc><additional n="Item description">The color images show indigenous catalogue marking in red ink "ka" (volume). Some parts of the texts are marked in yellow, or underlined in red.&#13;
Script: 'bru tsha&#13;
Lines per folio: 8&#13;
Folio numbering with numbers written in letters. From 100, number 100 is written as "+"; from 200, number 200 is written as "≠".&#13;
Orthography: &#13;
- Frequent abbreviations (e.g., for mngon sum, thams cad, etc.)&#13;
- Frequent superabundant suffix –'a (e.g., dbye', brda', gzhi')&#13;
- Frequent absence of g- prefixes (e.g., cig for gcig, sum for gsum)&#13;
- Alternative initial prefix (e.g., rngos or sngos for dngos)&#13;
- Bindu for m&#13;
- Alternative spelling (spyad for dpyad; spyod for dpyod; the tsom for the tshom)&#13;
- tsheg always present before shad (or double shad)&#13;
&#13;
Cover page: ex1301_20072023-06-281</additional></physDesc></sourceDesc>
      <respStmt><principal>
               <name ref="corpusmd:PH">Pascale Hugon</name>
               <name ref="corpusmd:KC">Kyeongjin Choi</name>
            </principal>
            </respStmt><respStmt><funder>
               <name ref="https://ror.org/0472cxd90">European Research Council</name>
               <name ref="https://kaken.nii.ac.jp">研究活動スタート支援 (Grant-in-Aid for Research Activity Start-up )</name>
            </funder>
            </respStmt></fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <tagsDecl partial="true">
            <rendition xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style:italics;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="u" scheme="css">text-decoration:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="b" scheme="css">font-weight:bold;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <projectDesc>
           <p>This document was created and is made available in the framework of the ERC
					project “The Dawn of Tibetan Buddhist Scholasticism (11th-13th c.) (TibSchol).
					This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under
					the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant
					agreement No. 101001002). See https://cordis.europa.eu/project/id/101001002</p>
               <p>It also benefitted from the work carried out in the project "チベット仏教カダム派の思想研究に向けた基礎資料の構築 (Construction of Basic Materials for the Study of the Thoughts of the Kadam School of Tibetan Buddhism) funded by the Grant-in-Aid Research Activity Start-up (No. 19K22998). See https://kaken.nii.ac.jp/en/grant/KAKENHI-PROJECT-19K22998/</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <variantEncoding method="double-end-point" location="external"/>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="apis" matchPattern="^(.+)$" replacementPattern="https://apis-tibschol.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/apis/api2/entity/$1/">
               <p>In the context of the TibSchol project, references using the "db" prefix
						point to the project's APIS instance, a database system to collect
						information of entities.</p>
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="per" matchPattern="^(.+)$" replacementPattern="https://www.tbrc.org/public?query=person&amp;args=$1">
               <p>In the context of the TibSchol project, references using the "per" prefix
						point to the BDRC's data interface's person module.</p>
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="zot" matchPattern="^(.+)$" replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/4394244/tibschol/items/$1">
               <p>In the context of the TibSchol project, references using the "zot" prefix
						point to a record in the projects's Zotero group.</p>
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="corpusmd" matchPattern="^(.+)$" replacementPattern="../010_manannot/corpus.xml#$1">
               <p>In the context of the TibSchol project, references using the "corpusmd" prefix
						point to any element in the corpus TEI document via its ID.</p>
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
			</profileDesc>
      </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><milestone unit="section" n="Cover page (1a)"/>
         <pb n="1a"/><lb n="1a1"/>
            <rs type="work" ref="db:4550" ana="corpusmd:named_reference"><rs type="work" ref="db:3774" ana="corpusmd:named_reference">
            tshad ma rnam par nges pa</rs>'i Ti ka legs bshad bsdus pa</rs> <rs type="person" ana="corpusmd:named_reference" ref="db:3839"><abbr>slob dpon</abbr> gtsang nag pa</rs>s mdzad pa <abbr>bzhugs s+ho</abbr> ||
            <lb n="1a2"/>
         i <choice><reg>dra sa</reg><orig>(dra sa)</orig></choice> <rs type="person" ana="corpusmd:named_reference" ref="db:4551">SHakya b+hikSHu ku ma ra SHrI</rs> pustaM <rs type="work" ref="db:4550" ana="corpusmd:named_reference"><rs type="work" ref="db:3774" ana="corpusmd:named_reference">pra ma Na bi ni <choice><reg>SH+ca</reg><orig>(SH+ca/s+tsa)</orig></choice> ya sya</rs> TI ka</rs> <rs type="person" ana="corpusmd:named_reference" ref="db:3839">A tsarya virya sing ha sya</rs> kA ra: ||<note type="editorial">Skt: idam? śākyabhikṣu-kumāra-śrī pustaṃ pramāṇaviniścayasya ṭīkā ācārya-vīryasiṃhasya kārāḥ. Kumāraśrī (=Tib. gzhon nu dpal) could possibly be 'Gos lo tsA ba bZhon nu dpal (ID:5839).</note><note type="translation">This is the book of the shakya monk Kumarashri (Tib. gZhon nu dpal), a commentary on the Pramāṇaviniścaya, a composition of the master Viryasiṃha (=brTson 'grus seng ge)</note></ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><milestone unit="section" n="A Incipit"/>
                <milestone unit="section" n="Title"/> 
           <pb n="1b"/><lb n="1b1"/><rs type="work" ref="db:4550" ana="corpusmd:named_reference"><rs type="work" ref="db:3774" ana="corpusmd:named_reference">tshad ma rnam par nges pa</rs>'i ti ka legs par bshad pa bsdus <choice><reg>pa</reg><orig>pa'</orig></choice></rs> zhes bya ba |
                   <milestone unit="section" n="Invocation"/> 
         <rs type="deity">bcom ldan 'das 'jam pa'i dbyangs</rs> la phyag 'tshal lo ||<note type="translation">Commentary on the Pramāṇaviniścaya – a summary of eloquent elucidations. I bow down to the Illustrious Mañjughoṣa.</note></ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><milestone unit="section" n="Introductory verses (1b1-1b5"/> 
        <milestone unit="section" n="v. 1"/> 
        <lg> <l>gang zhig nyes pa kun bral chos rnams la ||</l><l>ye shes spyan <choice><reg>dang</reg><orig>dang {ldan pa'}</orig></choice>  thugs rje'i gsung dbyangs kyis ||</l><l>legs 'dod skye bo don la mi slu ba'i ||</l><l>'jug yul <rs type="deity">ston pa</rs> <lb n="1b2"/> de la phyag 'tshal lo ||</l></lg>
        <note type="translation">I bow down to the one who teaches the object of engagement that is non-erroneous with regard to the goal of people who wish well,
         Through the melodious voice of compassion,
         With the eye of wisdom on the phenomena free from all faults.</note>

  <seg type="excerpt" xml:id="ex1301_1282023-4" status="reviewed" part="M" next="ex13012023-07-2008-36-52">
</seg>
<milestone unit="section" n="v. 3"/> 
         <seg type="excerpt" xml:id="ex13012023-07-2008-36-52" status="reviewed" part="M" next="ex01301_2025-11-2609-41-61"> </seg>
        <seg type="shared" xml:id="ex01301_2025-11-2609-41-61" status="reviewed" part="M" next="ex1301_10202023-06-285"/><milestone unit="section" n="v. 4"/> 
        <lg> <l>de lta'i gzhung 'di skye bo blo gros phyogs can gyis ||</l><l>
        tshig don ma bshad tshig dang don 'ga' bshad pa dang |</l> <l>log par bshad dang skabs don gzhung las 'khyams bshad kyis ||</l> <l>shes 'dod rnams kyi dus dang sgra blo gron gyur byas ||</l></lg><note type="translation">(Regarding) such a treatise, those of biaised understanding, 
Made those who whish to know waste their time, speech, and intellignece
By not explaining the meaning of words, explaining words and meaning partially,
Explaining them incorrectly, or explaining the contextual meaning in a way that deviates from the treatise.
</note> </ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><milestone unit="section" n="v. 2"/> 
       <lg><l>gang ma mthong pas srid par 'khyams gyur pa ||</l> <l>bdag la shes bya'i gnas la gnas nyid bzhin ||</l> <l>lta byed tshad ma'i myig gnyis sbyin mdzad pa'i ||</l>
            <l>rgyal mtshungs <rs type="person" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference" ref="db:4593">bla ma rnams</rs> la phyag 'tshal lo ||</l></lg>
         <note type="translation">I bow down to the bla mas, who are worthy of the Victorious ones,
Who bestowed the two eyes of valid cognition that make me,
Who is roaming in saṃsāra due to not seing it,
See the nature of objects of cognition as they are.
</note></ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><lg><l>gang zhig dngos stobs blo yis dngos rnams la ||</l> <l>log lta'i gzhung rnams rab 'jig dngos nyid dang ||</l> <l><lb n="1b3"/> <rs type="deity">ston pa</rs>'i gsung don nges byed rigs pa'i tshul ||</l> <l><rs type="person" ana="corpusmd:named_reference" ref="db:3773"><rs type="work" ana="corpusmd:named_reference" ref="db:3774">rnam nges</rs> mdzad pa</rs> de 'dir rgyal gyur cig ||</l></lg>
            <note type="translation">May the one who composed the Pramāṇaviniścaya be here victorious!
[The Pramāṇaviniścaya] that completely destroys the traditions of false views about entities 
By a mind based on the force of reality, 
The method of reasoning that ascertains reality and the meaning of the Teacher's words.
(Alternatively: May the one, who composed [the Pramāṇaviniścaya] ascertaining  
Reality completely destroying texts with false views about entities and, 
The method of reasoning determining the meaning of Teacher’s words 
Through the mind with the power of reality here, be victorious!)
</note></ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><milestone unit="section" n="v. 5"/> <lg><l>de dag rjes <lb n="1b4"/> zhugs dpyad la ltos myed par ||</l> <l>rnam 'jig sdud dang gzhung don gsal byed pas ||</l> <l><rs type="person" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference" ref="db:3773">ston de</rs>'i dgongs pa bde blag nges 'gyur ba'i ||</l> <l><rs type="work" ref="db:4550" ana="corpusmd:named_reference">legs bshad bsdus pa'i ti ka</rs> <rs type="person" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference" ref="db:3839">bdag </rs>gis bya ||</l></lg><note type="translation">Without relying on the analyses of these followers,
By including criticism of them and clarifying the meaning of the treatise,
I will compose a commentary that is an Eloquent Summary 
Easily confirming the intentions of the teacher (Dharmakīrti).</note></ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><rs type="work" ref="db:3774" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference">rnam par nges <choice><reg>pa</reg><orig>pa'</orig></choice></rs> ni lus lta bu'i bstan bcos bar ma ste | gzhung cung zad bsdus pas tshad ma nyid kyi lus tshang par gtan la 'bebs pa'i phyir ro ||</ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><rs type="work" ref="db:3774" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference">gzhung 'di </rs> ni rtsom pa la 'jug pa klad kyi don dang | brtsam par bya ba skabs kyi don dang | mthar phyin pa 'jug gi don gsum gyis nges par bya ba las |</ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><rs type="person" ref="db:4593" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference">snga rabs pa dag </rs>mtshan nyid kyi skyon mtshon bya la ltos te mi srid pa dang ma khyab khyab ches gsum las myed par sems pa de dag ni khyab mnyam pa'i don ldog gzhan pa dang rang ldog rdzas su ma grub pa skyon du bsgrub pas <lb n="11a2"/> gnod par lta'o ||</ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><milestone unit="section" n="1.1 so so'i ngo bo"/>
         <milestone unit="section" n="1 snang la ma nges pa"/> de la snang la ma nges pa'i mtshan nyid ni
         <rs type="person" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference" ref="db:4206">kha cig</rs> <note type="editorial">An annotation in the manuscript of mTshur ston's Tshad ma shes rab sgron ma identifies the proponent as "rtag pa," which we understand to refer to sTag. See Hugon (ed.) 2004: 21, n. 30</note> snang yang nges pa 'dren mi nus pa zhes zer ba ni 'dir blo rnams yul cig la ltos nas <lb n="22b8"/> tha dad par 'jog pa yin no ||</ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><milestone unit="section" n="2.1 mngon sum la log rtogs dgag pa"/>
         <lb n="24a6"/> dang po ni <rs type="person" ref="db:3786" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference">kha cig</rs> tshu rol mthong pa rnams ni yul dang dus dang skye mched ma phye bar gang la zhen pa drangs pa'i don la mi slu bas tshad mar 'gyur ba yin ste | zhen pa ni tshad ma'i byed pa yin pa'i phyir ro || de lta ma yin na 'gro ba na spyad pa'i don thob pa'i mi slu ba nyid mi srid par 'gyur te mthong pa'i dngos po rnams  <lb n="24a7"/> 'jug par gzo' ba na 'gag pa'i phyir ro || de lta yin dang me dang chu'i kha dog 'dzin pa ni tsha ba dang gsher ba'i zhen pa 'dren pa nyid kyis reg pa la tshad ma yin no zhes zer ro || <note type="editorial">This corresponds to the position of <rs type="person" ana="corpusmd:named_reference" ref="db:3786">rNgog lo tsa ba</rs> </note>
         de ni mi rung ste | don myong pa'i stobs kyis rtogs pa myed pa'i phyir ro || </ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><rs type="person" ref="db:5570" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference">snga rab pa pa</rs>'i 'dod pa rjes su brjod pa dang | sgrub bya sgrub byed kyi don nyid ngos gzung pa dang | de rang gi gzhung lugs smra ba rnams la sbyar ba'o ||
         </ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><rs type="person" ref="db:4593" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference">chen po dag </rs>ni sgrub pa 'brel pa gnyis la rten pas dbye ba'i tshul ci 'dra ba myed pas sam | mi dmigs pa'i sgrub bya med dgag la dbye' ba myed pa sam | dbye bsdu' byas kyang gsum gyi grangs <pb n="110a"/><lb n="110a1"/> nges la gnod pa myed te mngon sum bzhir phye bas tshad ma'i grangs nges la mi gnod pa bzhin no zhes zer ro ||</ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><rs type="person" ref="db:3839" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference">kho bo cag</rs> rtags mi 'khrul pa'i spyi khyab de nyid la 'brel par brjod pa'i yang phyir ro ||</ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><lb n="182b3"/> dang rang tshig gis bsal pa gnyis kyi khyad par ni <rs type="person" ref="db:4593" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference">snga rabs pa dag</rs> yid ches pa'i gang zag gzhan gyi tshig dang rgol ba rang gi tshig dang 'gal ba la 'jog go ||</ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><milestone unit="section" n="D Conclusive verses (209b3-210a3)"/>
         <!--Draft translation of the verses by Kyeongjin Choi-->
         <milestone n="v. 1" unit="section"/>
         <lg><l>rigs pa'i dbang phyug rgol <lb n="209b4"/> ba ngan 'joms thub pa'i dbang pos lung bstan gang ||</l> <l>ston pa'i bstan la mkhas pa'i nga rgyal dag gis ma smad cing <note type="editorial">2 syllables missing</note> ||</l> <l>'jug yul kun la rang gi lugs 'dzin skye bo kun kyi dbang gyur pa'i ||</l> <l>bla med de ni gling mchog 'di na <lb n="209b5"/> chos rje lta bur grags pa yin ||</l></lg>
         <note type="translation">The Lord of Reasoning (Dharmakīrti) is the supreme being renowned in this superior continent as the king of dharma, 
Who defeats the evil opponents, whom the Munīndra prophesized,
Whom those who have intellectual pride in the Teacher’s teachings do not blame, 
Who overpowers all those who hold their own theories regarding all object of engagement. 
</note>
<milestone n="v. 2" unit="section"/>
         <lg> <l>mtha' gnyis myed par gsum du 'khor zhing ××× mi bzad sdug bsngal rtag ldan pa ||</l> <l>thabs myed nyid dang thabs gzhan dag gis shin du zhi bar mi nus la ||</l> <l><lb n="209b6"/> blo gros snying po gcig nyid de yang gang zhig myed par mi 'byung pa'i ||</l> <l>rigs tshul 'di ni thar pa'i lam la mig dang snang pa seng ge yin |</l> </lg>
         <note type="translation">Without the two extremes, the way of reasoning—that is indispensable to rise even the essential wisdom 
To those whom, constantly accompanied with suffering and transmigrating in the three realms,
Could not be in the absolute peace by other means or no means—
Is the lion that is the eye and light on the path of liberation.
</note>
         <milestone n="v. 3" unit="section"/>
         <lg><l>gsum las bskyed de khyad par rnam bcad pas ||</l> <l>tshad ma'i ngo bo grangs <lb n="209b7"/> dang brjod pa la ||</l> <l>log rtogs brgya' phrag bsal nas rigs pa'i don ||</l>  <l>rnam par nges pa'i thub pa'i rgyal mtshan yin ||</l> </lg>
         <note type="translation">It (the Pramāṇaviniścaya) is the victory banner of the muni, 
Having eliminated numerous misunderstandings, determining the meaning of reasoning 
With regard to the nature, number, and explanation of pramāṇa 
By means of eliminating the specificities born from the three (realms?).
</note>
         <milestone n="v. 4" unit="section"/>
         <lg><l>mdo' don gsal byed don brgya' ldan pa don <choice><em>gyis</em><sic>gyi</sic></choice> gang ||</l> <l><lb n="209b8"/> rab sbyangs skye bo'i sgra blo 'i spyan dang ldan rnams kyis ||</l> <l>rnam par bshad pa che 'bring bsdus pa'i 'od dag gis ||</l> <l>rang gi phyogs su zla 'od tsam zhig snang bar byas ||</l></lg> <note type="translation">Lights of the extensive, middle, and condensed explanations 
By those who, with the eyes of words and intelligence, well learned the clarification/commentaries (gsal byed) that has a hundred meanings and were filled with meanings on the meaning of the Sūtra (i.e., the Pramāṇasamuccaya), 
Shone merely as the light of the moon on my side.
</note>
         <milestone n="v. 5" unit="section"/>
         <lg><l>de nas ring nas smon lam <pb n="210a"/><lb n="210a1"/> stobs kyis 'di 'ongs ste ||</l> <l>gang ri'i skye bo blo myig ldan pa stong dag gis ||</l> <l>phyogs cig blo yis gzhung dang don gyis cha shas las ||</l> <l>spyad mi rim pa don tshul rgya mtsho' gnyer ma 'gyur ||</l> </lg><note type="translation">Then, (I, gTsang nag pa) arrived here through the power of prayer for a long time. 
May a thousand people of snow mountains (Tibetans) with the eye of wisdom, 
Ripple the ocean of contents single mindedly, 
Through the stages of analysis from the aspects of texts and meanings.
</note>
         <milestone n="v. 6" unit="section"/>
         <lg><l><lb n="210a2"/> dus mtha' thos mang rnam spyad blo gros can ||</l> <l><rs type="person">dpal ldan dge' slong seng ge</rs>'i sgra can gyis ||</l> <l>dga' bas goms dang gzhan la phan don du ||</l> <l>ngo mtshar rmad kyi rnams bshad 'di byas so ||</l> </lg><note type="translation">Finally, (I), the glorious monk, 
Who is well learned, and endowed of analytic intelligence,
Holder of the roar of the Lion,
Composed this wonderful and marvelous commentary
For joyful practice and for the benefit of others.
</note>
         <milestone n="v. 7" unit="section"/>
         <lg><l>bsod nams 'di yis 'di la rab brten nas ||</l> <l><lb n="210a3"/> brtson ldan blo gros dman pa'i skye bos kyang ||</l> <l>rnam par nges pa nges ste shes bya'i ||</l> <l>de nyis myur du rtogs nas grol 'gyur cig ||</l></lg></ab>
      <gap reason="omitted"/>
      <ab><rs type="work" ref="db:4550" ana="corpusmd:named_reference"><rs type="work" ana="corpusmd:named_reference" ref="db:3774">tshad ma rnam par nges pa</rs>'i ti ka legs par bshad pa bsdus <lb n="210a4"/> pa</rs> zhes bya ba || <rs type="person" ref="db:3839" ana="corpusmd:unnamed_reference">rigs par smra ba'i dge slong brtson 'grus seng ge</rs>s sbyar pa'o || rdzogs s+ho || i thi || <note type="translation">Eloquent Summary – a Commentary on the Pramāṇaviniścaya, composed by the logician monk brTson 'grus seng ge. It is completed.</note></ab>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
